<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ux | Torstein Skulbru]]></title>
  <link href="http://tskulbru.github.io/blog/categories/ux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tskulbru.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-22T16:14:41+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://tskulbru.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Torstein Skulbru]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Material Design - We Live Only to Discover Beauty]]></title>
    <link href="http://tskulbru.github.io/blog/2014/09/22/material-design-we-live-only-to-discover-beauty/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T11:42:55+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://tskulbru.github.io/blog/2014/09/22/material-design-we-live-only-to-discover-beauty</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>&hellip; All else is a form of waiting</h1>

<p><img src="/images/materialdesign-goals-landingimage_large_mdpi.png" alt="Material Design" /></p>

<p>This quote by Kahlil Gibran suits the rapid development in design quality we&rsquo;ve seen in the digital space over the past years, we continue to see and experience really beautiful and contemplated design.
At this year&rsquo;s Google I/O, Google&rsquo;s design team presented the thing they&rsquo;ve been spending all their time on, &ldquo;Material Design&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been almost three years since Google presented their last UI change, &ldquo;Holo&rdquo;, which many of the popular apps on Android has tried to adopt.
Android apps used to be extremely fragmented when it came to design quality, but over the years as Holo has existed, more and more apps have that &ldquo;natural android look and feel&rdquo;. Most Android apps has moved away from the
&ldquo;no-design and shitty&rdquo; or &ldquo;ios-look-a-like&rdquo; infamous design quality in which the early apps had on the platform. Before this years Google I/O we all got a sneak peek at what we could expect from the design team with the release
of the new Google+ app, which drastically changed the look and feel of an Android app which we were so accustomed to.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/old-shitty-app.png' width='' height='' title='Shitty App Interface'><span class='caption-text'>Shitty App Interface</span></span></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/google-plus-holo.png' width='' height='' title='Google+ Holo Interface'><span class='caption-text'>Google+ Holo Interface</span></span></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/google-plus-paper.jpg' width='' height='' title='Google+ Paper Interface'><span class='caption-text'>Google+ Paper Interface</span></span></p>

<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;Our material is grounded in tactile reality, inspired by our study of paper and ink, yet open to imagination and magic&rdquo;</p><footer><strong>Google</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The entire interface is based on what Google calls a &ldquo;unifying theory of rationalized space and a system of motion&rdquo;. So what does all of this actually mean? Well what it essenctialy boils down to is bringing the interface in line with reality.
&ldquo;Material Design&rdquo; reacts to your touch by displaying a &ldquo;water ripple-like&rdquo; effect on touchable areas, it presents you with a feeling of depth by using z-index on certain elements. Animations are also heavily used (where appropiate of course), which is a big
change as Holo didn&rsquo;t really have any animations, and it was more up to each developer to include animations. I&rsquo;ve already mentioned the water ripple animation on touch, but there&rsquo;s so much more. I&rsquo;ll let the pictures explain for themselves.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/material_design_animation.gif' width='' height='' title='<a href="https://dribbble.com/shots/1717585-Google-s-Material-Design-Animation">Material Design Animation, by Balraj Chana</a>&#8217;><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://dribbble.com/shots/1717585-Google-s-Material-Design-Animation">Material Design Animation, by Balraj Chana</a></span></span></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/Menu&mdash;Back-Arrow.gif' width='' height='' title='<a href="https://plus.google.com/photos/+TaylorLing/albums/6037414075173412353">Actionbar Icon Animation, by Taylor Ling</a>&#8217;><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://plus.google.com/photos/+TaylorLing/albums/6037414075173412353">Actionbar Icon Animation, by Taylor Ling</a></span></span></p>

<p>Everytime I use an app which has Material Design, i smile. It&rsquo;s the coloring, the animations, the attention to details, just look at the blown up picture above of the menubar buttons. The animations are subtle, and Google really has put a lot of effort into documenting just
how, when, and for how long animation should be displayed.</p>

<p>Does this help with the earlier mentioned &ldquo;in line with reality&rdquo;?<br/> I&rsquo;ll leave that up for you to decide.</p>

<h2>Looks cool, now what?</h2>

<p>Earlier when it came to designing for Android, we didn&rsquo;t really have any resources available, except for the styleguide <a href="http://developer.android.com/design/get-started/principles.html">&ldquo;Android Design Principles&rdquo;</a>.
So this guy named, <a href="https://plus.google.com/+TaylorLing/">Taylor Ling</a> (you should probably write his name down) created a .psd file with a whole lot of Holo goodies, the <a href="http://androiduiux.com/2014/01/10/android-ui-design-kit-for-photoshop-4-4-free-download/">Android UI Design Kit</a>.
This really brought prototyping Android design to a whole new level. Suddenly you could quick and easily create prototypes which really looked like the end-product. This guy almost single-handidly changed the way designers prototype apps for Android.</p>

<p>It seems that Google and the Android team really saw something in all of this, and eventually not only made him a GDE, but with their announcement of Material Design, also released Illustrator files for all of the different components which makes up Material Design. I highly suggest
you all to take a look at their resources, <a href="http://www.google.com/design/spec/resources/layout-templates.html">here</a>. It&rsquo;s really simple, you just drag and drop the elements you want for the app you are prototyping, change some colors, and suddenly you have a beautiful prototype.</p>

<p>Using these resources, together with a little photoshop magic to create animations together with my prototypes, I&rsquo;ve been able to both shock, and awe clients.
Material Design is so thouhgt-through that I don&rsquo;t really need to think that much on design, colors, and structure as I used to, as long as I follow the guide presented to me. Eventually I will of course need to slightly diverge from the guide to suit the needs of my clients,
but still, building on top of Material Design I can still easily achieve a beautiful app.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a guideline, it&rsquo;s there to help you, not constrict you.</p>

<h2>The future</h2>

<p>Google obviously wanted to close the gap between Web, Android and iOS design. I feel like Apple wanted to catch-up with the &ldquo;flatness&rdquo; of Windows Phone and Android with their iOS7 release last year, and now Google wanted to try and stabilize the different platforms.
Thats the beauty of Material Design, it works perfectly on all platforms. It&rsquo;s not as it used to be where if an app on Android had iOS design it would stand out like a sore thumb, not to mention if anyone would be ballsy enough to have Android design on iOS.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
